

Saumitra Mazumder



SAMazumder



SAMazumder

About Me ————

Experience in model development and model validation/audit. Solid knowledge of a range of quantitative finance, risk management (e.g., VaR/Expected Shortfall for Market Risk, credit portfolio models, stress testing), derivatives models and pricing theory. Thorough and analytical; able to applying logic to solve problems. Excellent verbal and written communication skills. Proven ability to collaborate effectively with diverse individuals and strengthen relationships to achieve well-designed solutions.

Education ————

M.Sc. Applied Mathematics **Toronto Metropolitan University** (formerly Ryerson University) 2020-2022 Ryerson Graduate Fellowship, Graduate Development Award,

Mathematics Graduate Award

B.Sc. Mathematics and Economics Toronto Metropolitan University (formerly Ryerson University) 2015-2019 Dean's List 2016, 2017 Ryerson Barbell Club, Ryerson Math Problem Solving Club

Knowledge

Financial Mathematics

Financial Time Series Analysis, Risk Measures, Derivative Pricing, Regression, Monte Carlo/Copulae/Variance-Covariance Methods.

Tools

R (Dplyr, QRM, xts, dynlm), Python (NumPy, SciPy, PANDAS, XG-Boost. SKLearn), MATLAB, LTEX, SQL.

Employment History

Current Ernst & Young LLP Toronto, Canada

Staff consultant in the Financial Services Risk Management Group -

Consulting Practice.

2022-2022 Scotiabank Velocity Intern - Model Audit, Credit Risk. Toronto, Canada

Member of the team auditing ECL models (PD, CCI, EAD, LGD) per IFRS 9 guidance provided by OSFI. Used internal audit methodol-

ogy to provide independent oversight of models.

Closed audit issues pertaining an end-to-end retail model proce-

dure.

2018-2022

Toronto Metropolitan University, Department of Mathematics

Graduate Research Assistant under Dr. Foivos Xanthos

Completed research in Functional Analysis and its use in coherent

and convex risk measures on L^p -spaces.

Developed empirical algorithms to implement general-moment mar-

ket risk measures using R and Python.

Analyzed financial data using non-parametric methods to demon-

strate the potential benefits of general-moment models.

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Lead tutorials for graduate and undergraduate courses. Marking and

test invigilation for assigned courses.

Teaching Assistant for various mathematics courses. In particular, assisted students in becoming familiar with fundamental and advanced statistical concepts like MLE estimation, hypothesis testing, linear and non-linear regression models and solving various statis-

tical problems using R.

Undergraduate Research Assistant under Dr. Foivos Xanthos

Completed research on time series, probability theory, functional analysis and their applications to financial instruments. In particular, modeled credit risk via the asymptotic single factor Vasicek

(Merton) credit risk model.

2012-2020

Sylvan Learning Centres, Mentor's Academy and The Academy for Mathematics & English Toronto, Canada

Tutor specializing in mathematics, chemistry, biology and physics.

Provided tutoring services to various centres across the greater

Toronto Area.

Major Projects

Graduate

Statistical Consistency of Lebesgue Measures

Thesis

When estimating the risk of a P&L from historical data or Monte Carlo simulation, the robustness of the estimate is important. Analyzed a refined notion of robustness that applies to tail-dependent law-

invariant convex risk measures on Orlicz spaces.

Thesis

Undergraduate An Extreme Value Analysis of Financial Time Series

A study of extreme movements in financial asset returns. Showed that asset returns will have extreme realizations with greater probability than predicted by Black-Scholes model. Modelled the proba-

bility of extreme movements using Extreme Value Theory.